Welcome back, friends, taking on the discussion forward will now come across loops in Java and as like other C style languages where you have the for loop, the while loop, the do while loop, you have them in Java as well in addition to those traditional loops, we have some more that were introduced in in some of the recent versions in the language and I'll keep you updated as promised with all of those changes.
But for now we'll just start with those three and those are the four and the while and the do while and just to demo those I'll just get a new class again.
And let's just call it or loops work.
And let's put in the main method.
And as I said, we have the for we have the while we have the do while right just put in the comments the three loops that we start with and first things first, why would you ever want to use a for or a while or a do while or any loop for that matter is because you want a particular statement or a set of statements to be repeated and number of times you don't want to do it.
Like a donkey, you don't want to write repetitive you tedious code, but just do it in the most minimalist fashion and to start with with the for loop and let's say we have to print a series from one to 17 doing it through a for loop, the syntax looks like this, I just say paint value.
I used we and i and j to keep it in context always put in a procreate identifier names right these small attention to details would take you a long way ahead in your career, trust me on that.
So in value equal to one at starting point will say value is less than or equal to 17 the end point and then we do the increment or the agreement and here, even if you do the prefix.
So operator or use the post fix doesn't matter and then you go on and just slide in the line or the lines you want it to be repeated I just want to repeat the value of value.
So this is the starting point right and this is the condition and this is the agreement agreement.
Like the initialization part is encountered and it utilizes the value to one then goes to one to the condition if the condition is true goes directly to the body executes those line lines and then comes back to the increment or the agreement part then the condition then the body until the condition remains true.
As the condition is false the loop control gets you out of the loop okay so let's quickly go and run this and as you see in my output we get from one to 17 because at 80 this condition is false and it just comes out of the loop.
And let's say you want to print numbers alternately so what you would do is you will just say value plus equal to two remember I totally got compound operator so this is the first.
So you want to print only even numbers in the series or numbers in the series, you know how to tinker with this to just go on and do the hands on after this video or if you're just coding with me.
It was this video and do do the hands on every now and then so similarly we have the while loop and the syntax is different than a for loop and what you do is you just say while and then condition in that set.
The initialization is is thought to be done before the value starts the condition is here the increment agreement is set to be done in the while you right it's not part of that while line okay.
If you want to do the same thing I say into value to one and you would say value is less than equal to 17 and I'll say a sound just printed value and then I would have said our value plus plus or as I said, it's equal to.
Again, the appropriate white spaces to make your code better readable let's run this out and you would see the same output. So now you might be wondering when would we as a developer use a for loop over a while loop or vice versa that depends on your requirement and that depends on your style your preference.
The real thing is to write better readable code after this video i'm going to put you through an exercise where you would do it both ways for loop and while loop and then tell me which one is better for that kind of a situation.
So as a developer you have all the tools at your disposal which one to use when you would decide that individually and then we total third loop that is the do while and the syntax is different okay with a violent for but instead of just being the syntax being different.
I'll say a loop has a significant difference as well let's have a look at that i'll say a do and again like the while loop a do while says that the initialization part should be outside of the loop increment agreement within the loop and the condition is after the loop.
So again do something similar i'll say int value one and then I'll say a sound within the loop i'll say value because this is what I want to repeat and then value.
plus equal to two and then the condition is while value stays less than or equal to 17 prints the same thing if you run this.
So, no differences but a do while loop works differently it says directly first go in and do this stuff right but as you saw with a while and a for the condition was checked before the loop going inside the body with the while the condition was checked first but with the do while syntax the syntax is written in that way that the condition would be checked at last so.
In what situation when you prefer using a do while loop over a while and the for is when you want at least the loop to be run once so repeat after me a do while you runs at least once.
So, for programs such as menu driven programs when you want the menu to be printed at least once and then depending on a user action you might want to prefer a do while you so these are the three loops in the language to start with but as I said more up my sleeves later on.